hello it's February 15 2023
were in
cohort 2 of the octave textbook
we are in our first discussion on
chapter seven
so let's just first look at how chapter
7 is anticipated in the text
then any of you are welcome to give some
thoughts or just raise any thoughts or
questions on chapter seven
and then that will go wherever it goes
we can also look at previously submitted
questions as well as walk through the
text and get a big picture of what's
happening so the first mention of
chapter 7 is in chapter one when they're
summarizing chapter seven
and they describe that in chapter seven
they're going to discuss active
inference models addressing problems
formulated in discrete times
as hidden Markov models and partially
observable Markov decision processes
and they mention the examples they're
going to use which is a left or right at
A T maze
and they also bring in topics
information seeking learning novelty
seeking
they talk about how preference
represented by the C parameter is going
to be unpacked in chapter seven
in chapter four
they talk about how message passing
will be unpacked further in chapter
seven
in chapter five
they talk about e and policy so as
they're mentioning a bunch of the
parameters e Pi C
message passing they're describing that
they're going to come back to it in
chapter seven
um if we want to change the way the
signal is interpreted we need to rely on
learning we will return to this in
detail in chapter seven
in chapter 7 we will discuss a
biologically plausible example of
factorization
specifically the what and the where
streams
and in chapter 6 in the recipe
they talk about the updating in the form
of the updating
so several more mentions of chapter
seven in chapter six
and then we actually get to chapter
seven itself
all right so
anyone just to begin with
what were your thoughts or feelings on
reading chapter seven or what
came to mind as you read or
remembered reading
chapter 7 active inference in discrete
time
just on me and go for it
yeah well I I didn't read it completely
but there's a number of questions that
popped up in for instance in figure
seven three
um
so the a matrix is conditioned not only
on one state but a couple of states
is that correct I know I mean
it's uh so the the sequence of
preceding States
uh takes uh well is there place a role
that's different to Hidden Markov model
right
and then
so this would be one question how this
could be and then my another question is
whether this pie
actually makes this whole automaton more
powerful or
is this just a convenient way of uh of
representing it
so
um so could this pie actually be merged
in into the state as an additional
factor or something so multiply the
number of states and or does it really
increase the computational power of that
whole automaton
great questions
all right so yeah yeah Jacob go for it
first
um
I think that the
in terms of putting the pie into the
states themselves
um
I I don't I don't think I've seen that
ever being
um done in an actual model and I think
this is more of
a representation rather than really how
the model would be implemented because
the pie is just
is just the policy and it's I think it's
uh it like branches out to the two the
two B's uh from like a single node only
to represent that each B is also
conditioned on the policy
uh but not necessarily that
um
it's like a one
that that it happens within like one
time snapshot
yes
yeah in in some other work Jacob and I
have talked a lot about like why is pi
shown to intervene twice and even more
generally why is it shown with three
time steps yes it helps us understand
that it's like past present and future
but the action perception Loop also
could be shown
with just the transition between two
steps
and Pi intervening once
whereas this is a little bit ambiguous
whether it's a policy of length two
intervening at this time point
or whether it's just showing the
continual unfolding
of policy
interleaving between the hidden States
in a sort of open-ended way
um
but
what what do you mean Michael by
increasing the computational power
um I mean it it would be possible to
have the
uh dynamics of the Hidden States through
b
complex
but by removing pi and the action
selection apparatus
then if we only had the rake
down below
it would just be a passive inference
uh algorithm with a potentially complex
endogenous dynamic
well I I had the can I give an example
yeah oh yeah
so I I was thinking of so there is that
some kind of recursion possible for
instance I was thinking of the following
example assume that I want to
go and buy a bread
and then I go out and then on my way to
the bakery I see a haircut and I think
oh before buying this bed I could go to
the Hakata and then crossing the street
I see um
um uh
a shop with journals and then I think oh
when I sit there with a haircut I should
maybe buy a journal to read something
then I go to that journal I see a friend
and the friend tells me oh I have a new
car you want to come to see my car and
so I passed the half of the day going
forward and then eventually I backtrack
coming back from the car going by going
to the haircutter buying the bread and
in the evening I go home so this is a
kind of a recursive thing right so so
there is an action and then it there's
an intervention with another action but
then there is uh so it's a kind of a
recursive thing and each of those
actions maybe follows a policy but that
can be
there there can be another policy that
inter intervenes but then I backtrack
from there so that would actually be um
yes a recursive
a kind of a policy is is something like
this possible so this would really I
guess
um increase the computational power
um
with respect to just
completing one policy or one sequence of
actions and then going to the next where
you know where one iterates the stuff
instead off
the possibility to do that recursively
so there's something like this I was
thinking so is it possible to have some
recursive
policies there
one question I mean with no is to to
live stream 42 which was on Robotics and
the slam simultaneous localization and
mapping
there's a higher level policy selection
around what location the robot wants to
go and then a lower level tactical level
that is about the actual motor actuation
so in that example that you gave
there might be like a higher level model
of which location you want to go towards
and then there's a lower level footstep
model
and then this decision this shifting of
decision
could be modeled as policies on which
location one is seeking
so as with many features it's not
necessarily intrinsic to this figure 7.3
as the kernel but you can compose it in
order to capture some of those Dynamics
Ali and then Jacob
it
uh yeah well actually I think uh uh
described in those terms I mean uh
recursively updating uh the generative
model uh is just uh for the it can just
be for the purpose of building a
comprehensive uh generative model I mean
as comprehensively as we can but when we
include the policies
as the additional parameter in our
generative model uh actually this is a
kind of
um a technique used for bring the
elements of action selection uh two or
um within the the Bayesian belief
updating which is called the planning as
inference so in order to do that
uh policy selection or
I mean constructing a space of all
possible actions uh is a necessity a
requirement to do to do these uh kinds
of planning as inference but yeah it's
just a kind of uh mathematical uh trick
if you will uh to somehow bring together
uh the action selection into the
mechanism of uh Bayesian belief updating
but but this this possibility oh sorry
continue
yeah so so this possibility is not in
picture seven three right so because
these arrows go from PI
to the B Matrix but there's not a kind
of an error going back so
so if I are you saying the trick would
be that
one learns
a pie inside a pie
somehow
yeah you see this is just one policy a
picture a snapshot of a one policy uh
but uh in the more comprehensive models
we have uh the state of possible and I
mean uh we have policies and not just
one single policy to select from so yeah
that's just that picture just shows how
uh the uh I mean choosing a single
policy can affect uh the uh generative
model and how it can do the inference
via planning or action selection but in
reality or I mean uh when dealing with
more comprehensive uh models
we have uh not we don't necessarily have
just one single policy to do uh to uh
select from I mean uh it would be
tautological to have just one single
policy so we need a space of uh
possibility yes
if there was just one policy
and there is no agency around selecting
it
then it reverts to a passive inference
challenge
whereas the structure of the B Matrix
which you can explore from a Hands-On
perspective like by looking at the
dimensionality of it in piodp
the inference problem is set up such
that agents are deciding between pi 1
and Pi 2 which are evaluated according
to their expected free energy and Pi 1
and Pi 2 do different things
to be
so we can think of like a B1 and B2 not
time point one and two but variant or
slice one and two
that
change how hidden States change their
time so Jacob
um
I guess on the question of
um like recursion and
uh with your example of like going to
um
to a barber and then seeing oh
um I want to buy a magazine to read and
like going the policy changing
throughout
I guess
I'm not
uh I'm not really sure I see the
recursion there in in like an active
inference model because I think it's
more
I'd say it's more like a very high
dimensional model where you are perhaps
performing
uh where you're always like narrowing
down your policy search space
um
and with new observations you're like
adjusting that search base based on your
preferences in that particular
uh observational modality like you get
reminded that there are magazines and
that you can buy magazines to read
uh while you're at another place so it
kind of extends that computation but I
don't think it's necessarily
um recursive and also
I think the
the figure
um I think you mentioned something about
like uh
prediction errors or uh so something
like that I don't think that's
necessarily captivated in the figure
because that only shows well I I guess
it's not explicit but it we can assume
that the B There is static and you can
imagine
a lot of other things happening if you
would be learning the B major fix or
doing uh model selection as well
um and adjusting your policy based on
what observational modality has the
um
highest
um precision
and can I answer uh yeah to this so so I
think
well maybe you can represent this in a
in a way of an iteration or the way you
say but it it would be recursive in my
understanding of the these terms if if
if going for instance to the baker is is
a policy means it's a series of actions
right and so if this is a policy and
then in the middle of this there is
somehow another policy that pops up oh I
go first to the hair cutter or to the
barber whatever and then
this uh one policy still exists but
inside there's another kind of sequence
of actions another plan and so on
popping up and this if this could happen
recursive I mean in my understanding of
this term of um of these terms uh it it
would be kind of recursive
no
yeah yeah it can be through nested
modeling which is one canonical way that
recursion is implemented so it's it's
unfolding sequentially Through Time
but also like this higher level
um discrete time so that's again we're
chapter seven we're in discrete time
and so this might be a slower click
so maybe the footsteps are taking place
on a second to Second policy tick
timeline
whereas a policy in which location one
wants to go is being evaluated at a
slower level
and if the if this nested level
is playing out at at um a similar
frequency
to the lower level
than
um as a modeler you might be better off
just having it as a single level model
and as an organism you'd get into these
kind of like paralysis
cases where if you're actually switching
policies about where you want to go
then this would be incoherent down a
lower level
um
so just return to the initial question
is it possible to merge policy into the
hidden States as as a causal latent
factor well in a way policy intervenes
in how hidden States through change
their time so policy does influence
hidden States
without an action selection apparatus
it's not active inference it's not even
a control theory problem it's just a
question of identifying latent causes
from the unfolding of a hidden States
and observables that you can't control
and that's a classical SPM type
challenge like s might be the latent
unobserved neural activity and O might
be multi-sensor fusion with fmri EEG and
Meg
so this can still be very complex in its
unfolding through time with the
observations in the hidden States
what would make it an active inference
problem well if you weren't just
observing sensor modalities
but if the experimenter could take a
policy
that was intervening how neural Dynamics
change through time which is what
experimental design is which is why it's
so compatible with thinking about
um
the metabasian approach with the
behavioral researcher
so apply influences hidden States
but if we merely folded
into B we would lose the ability to do
actual action selection
but if it were a passive inference
problem
we still could use variational inference
we still could use a free energy
we still could even align outcomes with
our preferences we could still calculate
and bound surprise
the active embedding of active inference
is to include action as a parameter like
Ali mentioned within the Bayesian brain
context
to have a parameter that you do Bayesian
inference on
and then extend that not just from
perception and causal inference which is
what's happening on the bottom
like perception is the a
causal inference can be understood as B
but action selection does require an
additional apparatus
passive inference more like signal
processing
action more like control theory
unified imperative
so the G would then be predicting the
future of expectations developing of
expectations and so on
what would it be
what is g the G the pi
oh sorry oh
well pi
is the combinatorics of affordances over
a given time Horizon
so merely generating pi as a list
is not intrinsically difficult it's just
the search space of possible action
sequences over a given time Horizon
if there's two options and you're doing
a Time Horizon of three then it's two
cubed
um G is the expected free energy
which updates the policy prior
so take that list and it's your prior
probability of those policies
which could be either just a uniform
prior
or
could reflect habit
like a priori How likely are policies
and then G
sharpens or updates
that policy vector
into a policy posterior which then the
agent samples their actions from
and and how um how is this meant so I
assume that I'm so you're saying the
first is the past and then um so is this
um
is this re re-estimated at every state
so so the Spy would somehow
have um expectations of a future
affordances as you say right
but would say which which transitions
are more likely in the
uh to the right of this graph
and would that be re-estimated in at
each time
um
time step or okay how would that yeah
there's there's multiple possible levels
only go first then I'll give a thought
well basically Pi actually is just an
additional parameter uh multiplied to
the basic uh Bayes theorem formula we
had before so instead of just
multiplying likelihood and uh the priors
simply we also multiply the probability
of selecting a policy and that's just it
so Pi is just an additional parameter in
that equation from chapter back in
chapter two
yeah
equation 2.6
is where G is defined
so G is a a function of policies
so it takes in as arguments the vector
of policies
and then conditioning as we see in every
single of these phrasings
every single one is conditioned upon a
given policy
and then different policies
are compared
by their expected free energy
and then depending on the Precision on
the action posterior
which isn't shown in 7.3 you can have a
spectrum of behavior if you have
extremely high precision
like a um it could be thought of as low
temperature
in that case
one policy that's let's just say one is
um it's one percent better than the
other then under the low temperature
asymptote the high Precision asymptote
the policy that's even tiny tiny bit
better will always be selected
under the neutral temperature
Zone
policies are selected based upon their
posterior likelihood so if one of them
is 51 percent and the other is 49 when
you soft Max it then it's selected
51 and 49 of the time respectively and
then in the high temperature or low
Precision asymptote
also known as shaky hand
the differences amongst policies in
their expected free energy basically get
erased
and at that point
policies are selected
essentially without respect to their
posterior likelihood
this is one of the key pieces though
because again we're not calculating
different policies and asking well how
rewarding are they how much expected
reward do they have and then ranking or
selecting based on that
rather
there's a unified imperative expected
free energy
which under different decompositions can
be shown to have these different
interpretations
that is then used to generate a policy
posterior and then as just described
that policy posterior in the context of
a of a temperature or Precision variable
can exhibit behaviors ranging from
always selecting the slightly preferred
policy in the low temperature limit
neutral temperature selecting according
to the posterior high temperature
erasing differences in the posterior Ali
yeah uh sorry I just wanted to point out
that uh this G Matrix here is uh still
prior to learning so uh if we want to
add learning to uh to into the policies
uh things would get a little bit more uh
not to say complicated but more extended
equations would be needed so uh we
haven't included learning in this
specific formulation yet it's prior to
learning
yes thanks yeah I I um I also want to
highlight that like
in in the category of phenomena that we
can model but are not just simply in
this image
you mentioned like learning new policies
so it's like in the fixed fixed fixed
case
you're still able to do action selection
but you're not learning or changing
which policies you can enact you're not
changing what affordances you believe
you have nor are you updating B which is
to say you're not updating your beliefs
about how policies influence hidden
State changes
the next level of introduction of
novelty is learning on B
where you can learn about the different
consequences of policy and then another
level which is starting to approach into
like the structural learning because
you're actually changing not just
parameters within the model but
dimensionality of parameters within the
model is like well what if I take a
policy that opens up another set of
possible policies
so this is like see the cat run
of sentences
and to introduce recursive or
referential Clauses or learning it's a
more complex sentence so to speak
but this is the archetype that sets the
stage for what cognitive model
structures could exhibit that kind of a
phenomena Michael
yeah so
um a policy
would be a number of actions right would
be a sequence of States yeah is is that
am I understanding correct and if this
is the case then a policy would select a
number of states
and my question I guess is
um so then I come at the end or at what
point are these policies then uh
calculated so I come to the end of my uh
of a of an action and then only is the
uh it's the it's a new um policy uh a
computer or selected or is it constantly
the case
so if um if I decide to to go to buy a
bread for instance and then I go out and
I cross the street and do this and that
so there's a couple of actions involved
right and so my decision to buy a bread
was done before but on the way
um is that policy recalculated and maybe
on on the way I think oh I um
uh something else is is more reasonable
to do
um
okay so again that's it's a slightly
nested scenario with with multiple
levels of policy that you're
um looking at and then just to be clear
so policy it's a sequence of actions so
let's just say that the affordances
there's two affordances up or down
and then time Horizon is three
well let's just say it's two
there are four policies you you d d u d
d
so generating the state space of
policies
is trivial
it's just all of the strings of
affordances
now you ask where does policy inference
happen where and how does it happen and
there's a few different answers so first
off here's from our active inference and
modeling conflict paper here we chose to
show only a two-step model
so instead of the the three because we
were anticipating that
um ambiguity
where Pi is intervening twice when
actually control is only exerted at any
given moment but it's it's
anticipated
um and then we map this onto the UDA
observe Orient decide act this isn't a
formal mapping per se but it it helps
understand sequentially for example in a
reactive message passing paradigm
what different informally
categorized states of the perception
cognition Action Cycle how that maps
onto this basing graph so since States
come in
cognition on occurs
or one could also take a broader
perspective then but this updates one's
beliefs about the world
then there's an inference on action
so here are the antecedents of policy
selection which are
e what can be done the affordances
see what is preferred the preferences
preferred slash expected
and then with c and e
as it shows here
G is a function
of policies conditioned upon c and e
so with those antecedents taken care of
we can update our beliefs on pi
to move from a policy prior
to a policy posterior
those policy posteriors can then be
sampled from as discussed earlier at
high low or neutral temperature
and then the selected policy
intervenes and ends up choosing a slice
in b
and then the slice of B that's chosen
influences how the hidden States change
for example if there's two Paul if
there's two policies on a one-time step
basis so same as the affordances in this
case turn on the heater or do not turn
on the heater
so maybe if we don't turn on the heater
then the B Matrix just passes the hidden
State forward the temperature doesn't
change
if we do turn on the heater the
temperature increases immediately again
simple example
so
we looked at the thermometer oh
updated our belief given our priors
about the temperature of the room
then with respect to what we can do e
and what we expect slash prefers C
we updated our policy prior into a
policy posterior
we then selected the action
that's most likely
not the most rewarding action
the most likely action
and that influenced how the hidden
States changed their time
and then the UDA cycle begins again
so action intervenes
in the discrete time formalization which
is where we're in chapter seven
it intervenes in every time click
okay thank you so much
and and also um the pragmatic turn
is um it's a book co-edited by friston
but it discusses like
what
has happened in Neuroscience with people
embedding action and thinking about
action in neuroscience
and that's relatively recent which is
really exciting
okay but these are these are great
questions and then let's just also go to
the um
second question that you raised there
and then we'll scan through all of
chapter seven
so is the a matrix in figure 7.3
conditioned on one state or a series of
States so
yes
Jacob feel free to add any more details
on this one but as it's shown here from
a base graph perspective
it is O of T minus 1 is only conditioned
on S of T minus 1.
but when we think about across the
vector of observations
they can be understood as being
conditioned upon
the time series of hidden States
so each observation is only conditioned
upon its Associated hidden State that's
the partially observable and hidden
States
pass through the Markov needle of the
presence that's the markovian property
past only influences the future through
the present
which isn't to say that's how reality is
that just to say it's a simplifying
structural assumption
that one could vary if they chose
but it is a little ambiguous I I I can
see why somebody might think that
observation at a given t
let's say t plus one is can is a
function that's conditioned upon all the
previous types
but not directly
observations are like cul-de-sacs
and again a is The Tail of Two densities
the recognition density which is from
observations updating beliefs about
hidden States
Bayesian recognition model
and the generative density which is from
a hidden state
generating pseudo-observations
and the way that those two densities
can be alternated
is used and has been used for decades in
expectation maximization algorithms
okay
cool great
questions here
um
does anyone want to go to any
of the chapter 7 questions or should we
scan through in the last 15 minutes here
just like what happens in chapter seven
foreign
Let's scan
raise your hands when you want and I'll
immediately go to you
if you want to
um just add a note on like as we scan
through so we will scan through the
whole thing in the next 10 minutes okay
starting with a quote what I cannot
create I do not understand famous
quote
take it or leave it
but now we're into the building the
recipe has been disclosed in chapter six
the prerequisite knowledge has been
distributed in chapters one through five
ideally
they start with perceptual processing
this is very much like the step-by-step
paper
step by step starts even simpler with
starting with just a static inference
but here they go immediately to Dynamic
perceptual inference this is just the
bottom of the rake this is a passive
inference
but it is changing through time
they're going to be using a music
example
speaking to their target audience which
is Ali
um a musical example
so we're listening to some music
not necessarily playing
um the music
but the outcome is the note that's
actually intended I'm sorry the outcome
is what is actually played and the
hidden state is the intended note
and just from looking at this a matrix
we can see that like on the diagonals if
it was the identity Matrix
that would mean that there was a perfect
mapping between hidden State and
observations but this is not an identity
Matrix it has off diagonal values which
is to say it's like a blurry a matrix
and in the limit of a blurry a an
ambiguous a
you could imagine if it was all 2.5S
across
then there would be no information on
hidden State given the outcome
The Other Extreme would be perfect
information with the identity Matrix and
you can see that it's also rescaled so
the numbers can be shown kind of Simply
as integers
and then it's rescaled so that it's a
proper probability
so seventy percent of the time the
musician hits their intended note
Row one column one seven
B is the probability of transitions
so we can go if we go from Node 1 to
Note 2 with 97 so notice the diagonal
if that was the identity Matrix on B if
that was all B was
you would basically dwell wherever you
began
if b is all off diagonal you never stay
in the same spot twice
and so here is a sequence
of notes because one almost always moves
to two two almost always moves to three
three almost always moves to four and
four almost always moves to one
then D is the prior and so it's just
being taken as a noiseless estimate that
the first note is the beginning note
Michael
so is this a very boring tune that plays
Four notes in the in the round
eternally
exactly like this it's like Geb in
Eternal Golden Braid except it's like g
e b
x g e b x okay very boring yeah okay yes
it is a simple one
so 7.1 to 7.3 equations completely
specify the hmm note that it's a hidden
Markov model
because it has this partially observable
character but it's not a decision
process because there's no action
selection but all we needed to do was to
specify a b and d
so to totally specify the hmm was ABD we
didn't have to say which notes we
preferred we didn't have to say anything
about what we could do with C or E
okay
then there are some simulations shown
um there's a few things about this
simulation first as the earlier question
has raised why are there continuous
interpolations when we're in the
discrete time world
a general comment is these graphs with
multiple block lines
are a little hard to interpret because
of course we can't tell which line is
which
another issue with 7.2 figures
specifically is the bottom left quadrant
is empty
so just a few points but what's
basically happening is in this
simulation run which would only happen
this way
um several percent of the time but
they're showing it
um basically
um in the upper right
um
the retrospective beliefs are shown
so the retrospective beliefs
are shown with a correct song
even though the actual observations were
were note one two two four
so this observation
was recognized and it did increase the
posterior on Note 3 being played
however because the belief was so strong
that belief that Note 3 would be played
in this time
it did not move the needle far enough to
actually hear that note
so that's like when somebody hears
something that isn't said because it's
likely that it was set
okay so that's a fun model but it's not
action inference yet so that's where we
get to 7.3 where we've been spending a
lot of today's discussion
7.3 discusses the addition of an extra
variable on which transition
probabilities are conditioned so it's
like really when we think B we should
really think B vertical line pi
because the inference on action means
that if that we have actual options for
action
which is to say
there are multiple B's that can
influence how s unfolds
so we're really talking about B's
condition on on policy unless we're
talking about like the whole B
caterpillar the whole tensor of B
foreign
here's where
um expected free energy
and one of the partitionings is shown
which is discussed in chapter two
equation 2.6 and in chapter four so next
week when we're in chapter seven for the
second time let's can let's return talk
a little bit more about the technical
parts of like what exactly equation 7.4
means
um
it's a decomposition
that enables epistemic drive towards
information gathering that's this first
part of the right hand side and the
pragmatic Drive
which is about
realizing prior beliefs
reducing surprise about prior beliefs
not maximizing a reward function
reducing diversions between preferences
and outcomes
they're going to unpack the full
7.3 figure
in the context of a t mace which is a
rat that's able to go left or right to
find food or not
or it's able to get a cue
that's the Q location r
there's four locations that it can be in
and there's modular degrees of freedom
in how different things are represented
so this isn't even the only way to
represent this
toy example
but this Matrix does a really good job
of showing like
what are the states what are the
dimensionality
of the difference variables which we can
come to next week
so here's context two here's context one
here we have block on the right side
white on the left
here we have block on the left white on
the right
and there are some subtle differences
which you can note like specifically
with lines two and three here's a one
here
here's a one on the third line
because the Q is suggesting that it's on
the right
here the queue is showing it's on the
left and in model stream 7.2
that example is like very Hands-On and
in some ways even better than this one
and it includes things like learning but
it's a very similar task
here is B2
so they're showing the dimensionality of
what those B slices look like for
different policies
this is representing the B tensor
here are preferences
this is what a preference Vector looks
like and in step by step the paper and
model stream one series and in model
stream 7 Series there's some discussion
on what does c mean is it being
reflected as log probabilities
why would one do six and negative 6
versus 6 000 a negative 6000 or 0.6 and
negative point six what if those values
actually mean
and the prior is provided
so now that we've provided a
controllable B
which is the manifestation of policy
options
and provided a c
we can do active inference because we
have now
what we need
those two pieces really that's what
brought us from the hmm to the pomdp was
what we can do and what we prefer
um section 7.4 goes into information
seeking it unpacks the epistemic value
into a few more sub decompositions
and it talks about how that plays out
there's some Nuance here again there's
also some
semi-confusing black and white graphs
but other ones are clear
we can talk about how epistemic value is
being realized in this example
box one
is a a bit of a uh side note
on uncertainty and precision
and here's showing really the
temperature or the Precision highest
temperature
lowest entropy most uniform distribution
lowest temperature highest entropy most
specific distribution
here you're sharpening
here you're blurring
okay 7.9 as mentioned um
two pages earlier is an icicate
so
um
there are four locations
and the eyes are cicading again one
could ask about where are these
continuous interpolations coming from
since we're in chapter seven in a fully
discrete situation
but it's all good so isocating different
sequences or traces of isocades across
four locations
driven by epistemic value
in section 7.5
learning and Novelty is introduced so as
we were mentioning earlier learning with
respect to the a or the B Matrix
so far we've been talking about them as
fixed
here is where learning happens on a and
b and just like you would do with any
Bayesian inference whether on action or
on the consequences of action or on
perception
learning is modeled as a hyper prior or
a variable that governs a prior on
another parameter so here is like a
parameter
um that is adding a layer
to the rake we still see the core figure
4.3 figure 7.3 Motif but there are these
new little edges
that are the learning edges so it's the
same pumdp as figure 7.3
but the priors for each hidden States
now depend on the variables which
themselves come with prior beliefs so
the prior on the variables A and B
is in the Bayesian Paradigm how we learn
or update our values on a and b
um
brief discussion on College of priors
some more equations
that we can come to next week about
updating and learning on a
another look in equation 711
on G
which is very similar to what we saw in
equation 2.6 different partitionings on
expected free energy a policy
then there's a final example that's now
in a maze
and so this is some maze seeking entity
we can come to this next week
um in hierarchical inference
hierarchical or deep inference something
we kind of mentioned today but we'll
look more at next week
is um well first there's a box on
structure learning
which as mentioned earlier is when we
think about look regular non-structured
learning as like fine-tuning
quantitative parameters within a given
dimensionally defined generative model
structure learning and what you can do
with structure learning like
specifically Bayesian model reduction is
when we're actually modifying the
dimensionality of the generative model
that's in box 7.3
here is a nested generative model which
is almost exactly the form that we
looked at from live stream 42
where we see like the rake classical
figure 4.3 figure 7.3 Paradigm and then
there's like a meta break
where here's another E downward facing
and we have policy at a higher level and
different generative models have taken
different interpretations on what the
lower and the higher level are like in
live stream 42 the lower level was
tactical movement of a robot and the
higher level was strategic location
preference whereas in live stream 28
sandbed Smith at all the higher levels
were associated with attention in the
lower levels with perception
another example with decision making
will come to and then the chapter
summarizes so thank you for this session
we'll stop recording and take a break
before the next one